Everybody, today's דף daf is ע"ה. Ayin-Hey. We're a little behind, but
as I said, we'll be posting two דפים dapim a little later
today, so we'll be caught up, God willing. We pick up at
the very bottom of ע"ד עמוד ב' Ayin-Dalet Amud-Bet and we just
finished the whole discussion about יהרג ואל יעבור, yeihareg ve'al ya'avor, when
you're supposed to give up your life. And the basic conclusion is
in private just for the three big ones, עבודה זרה, avodah zarah,
גילוי עריות, gilluy arayot, and שפיכות דמים. shefichut damim.
But once it's in public and those are for a particular reason,
and once it's in public and it's done for the sake of
making a person transgress, so it's done as a way of undermining
the faith, or if it's just a general period of שעת השמד,
sha'as hashmad, then that becomes an act of קידוש השם Kiddush Hashem
and that's even for a minor thing. And we had an interesting
but important discussion when it's not שעת השמד sha'as hashmad in public,
it has to be specifically for the purpose of making somebody transgress,
not for הנאת עצמו, hana'as atzmoh, not for just doing it for
their own purposes. And we had a whole fascinating discussion about the
whole issue about women and קרקע עולם karka olam and is it
יהרג ואל יעבור yeihareg ve'al ya'avor or תהרג ואל תעבור. teihareg ve'al
ta'avor. Okay, and now we pick up with a different tack on
this. Okay, it says like this: בעי
מיניה, Bo minei, it is eight lines from the bottom. בעי מיניה
מרבי אמי, Bo minei mei-Rabbi Ami, they asked from Rabbi Ami. בן
נח מצווה קידוש השם או אינו מצווה קידוש השם, Ben Noach metzuveh
Kiddush Hashem o eino metzuveh Kiddush Hashem, is a בן נח Ben
Noach obligated to give up his life rather than transgressing one of
the שבע מצוות בני נח? Sheva Mitzvos Bnei Noach? Now first of
all, תוספות Tosafos asks how do we know, you know, why do
we start by assuming he's not and have to prove that he
is? Why don't we assume he's obligated to give up his life,
forget קידוש השם, Kiddush Hashem, because he's commanded. You know, by the
Jews we know you're not obligated to give up your life because
it says וחי בהם. v'chai bahem. But by non-Jews, it doesn't say
וחי בהם. v'chai bahem. So תוספות Tosafos sort of has, you know,
raised the question, but he basically concludes maybe you don't really need
וחי בהם, v'chai bahem, maybe you only need וחי בהם v'chai bahem
to counteract the idea that there's some מצוות mitzvos you're supposed to
give up your life for. But maybe we would have started even
without a verse to assume that you don't give up your life
for מצוות. mitzvos. So that seems to be the starting point anyway
by the בני נח, Bnei Noach, and the question is are they
obligated in קידוש השם? Kiddush Hashem? Now does the גמרא, Gemara, the
גמרא Gemara does not seem to mean specifically the three big ones,
although the בני נח Bnei Noach have the three big ones, עבודה
זרה, avodah zarah, גילוי עריות, gilluy arayot, and שפיכות דמים. shefichut damim.
So it could mean specifically about those three. But let's remember that
those three were not framed as issues of קידוש השם. Kiddush Hashem.
Those three were framed based on particular verses, meaning רוצח rotzeach is
about protecting the whatever, you know, it's like why do you think
your blood is any redder. The case of גילוי עריות gilluy arayot
was learned from that. עבודה זרה avodah zarah was based on אהבת
השם. ahavas Hashem. קידוש השם Kiddush Hashem specifically is in the context
of either שעת השמד sha'as hashmad or מכוון mechaven to make you
עובר, oveir, right, or, you know, aspects of like בפרהסיא, be-farhesya, מכוון
mechaven to make you עובר. oveir. So you would have to imagine
a case, for example, that what do you call it, that
some pagan government is trying to make the פרום frum non-Jews, you
know, violate their שבע מצוות Sheva Mitzvos or something of that nature.
Okay, but it's specifically a question of קידוש השם, Kiddush Hashem, presumably
about all
שבע מצוות, sheva mitzvos, not necessarily about the big three. Yes, Charlie?
This is the first time that קידוש השם Kiddush Hashem for non-Jews
has come up and we had pages of discussion of the שבע
מצוות בני נח Sheva Mitzvos Bnei Noach for
more than that, and it never came up.
Sure, because and we also have a ש"ס Shas that discusses the
תרי"ג מצוות Taryag mitzvos of בני ישראל, Bnei Yisrael, and קידוש השם
Kiddush Hashem only comes up in this context. So even though we're
talking about the other מצוות mitzvos here, we're talking about קידוש השם,
Kiddush Hashem, so here we're going to talk about it in terms
of non-Jews. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר אביי תא
שמע שבע מצוות נצטוו בני נח, Amar Abaye Tashma Sheva mitzvos nitztavu
Bnei Noach, there's only seven, ואי איתא תמני הווי, v'ee isa tamni
havei, according to you there's an eighth מצווה mitzvah called קידוש השם.
Kiddush Hashem. So אמר ליה רבא, Amar lei Rava, no, אינהו וכל
אביזרייהו. Inhu v'chol avizrayu. No,
no, no, when it says seven, it means sevens and their אביזרייהו,
avizrayu, its appurtenances and the things connected to them. Somebody was just,
who said it the other day, that in modern Hebrew אביזרי avizari
there's a word like אביזרייהו avizrayu in modern Hebrew, I think that
means like computer peripherals or something of that nature. Anyway,
so אביזרייהו avizrayu means the things connected with it. So if there's
a מצווה mitzvah to let's say, I don't know, not steal, so
the question of are you supposed to steal or not steal if
it's an act of קידוש השם? Kiddush Hashem? If there's a מצווה
mitzvah of, you know, of אבר מן החי, Aiver min hachai, so
do you do that or do you not do that when your
life is at stake? So that's an aspect you could see that
not only you could see it as an independent issue, but you
could see it as an issue that determines the scope of your
obligation within each of the שבע מצוות בני נח. Sheva Mitzvos Bnei
Noach. So the fact that it's not listed as an eighth isn't
a counter-proof. Okay,
so מאי הוי עלה? Mai hava lah? So what was the conclusion?
אמר אדא בר אהבה, Amar Adda bar Ahava, אמרי בי רב, Amrei
bei Rav, within the house of Rav, כתיב, kesiv, it says לדבר
הזה יסלח השם לעבדך. Ladavar hazeh yislach Hashem l'avdecha.
That was נעמן Naaman who accepted to not be עובר עבודה זרה,
oveir avodah zarah, the whole case where he was cured from his
leprosy and he says to אלישע, Elisha, he says for this one
thing I ask you to forgive me, בבוא אדוני בית רמון, bevo
adoni beis rimmon, when my master... The king goes to בית רמון,
Beis Rimon, this house of idolatry, להשתחוות שמה, lehishtachavos shama, to prostrate,
והוא נשען על ידי, v'hu nishan al yadi, and he's going to
like I'll be supporting him, והשתחויתי, v'hishtachaveisi, and I'll have to bow
down with him. וכתיב, U'ksiv, ויאמר לו לך לשלום. vayomer lo lech
l'shalom. He says, go in peace, it's fine, don't worry about it.
Okay, now this is very interesting because, well first of all, it
sounds like bowing down with him is an act of עבודה זרה,
avodah zarah, even though he's not doing it for the purpose of
עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, right, he's just doing it to help support
his king or whatever, you know, king shouldn't collapse, which is interesting,
that goes to the question about, you know, מאהבה ומיראה, me'ahavah u'meyirah,
right? He's not doing it as any act of worship, he's not
intending it as any act of worship, you know,
it's even less than that he doesn't believe in the god. He's
just really just doing it. You know, let's say you bow, the
גמרא Gemara has a דרשה drasha that you bend down to pick
up some money that fell before an idol. That's not an act
of עבודה זרה בשוגג. avodah zarah b'shogeg. It might look like it
to an onlooker, right, but it's not actually the act, it's not
intended as an act of worship. So that's fascinating, right, so that's
very fascinating in itself anyway. So it says, look, he's allowing it,
he's actually giving his blessing, you know, so it says, ואי איתא,
v'im issa, if there was an issue about קידוש השם, Kiddush Hashem,
לימא ליה, leima lei,
don't say to him לך לשלום, lech l'shalom, like רש"י Rashi says,
okay, he might not have an obligation to be מוכיח mochiach him,
maybe הוכח תוכיח את עמיתך hocheiach tochiach es amisecha doesn't apply to
a non-Jew, you know, but don't give him your blessing. Giving him
your blessing seems like it's all okay. So the גמרא Gemara says,
now wait a minute, maybe we could say there's a difference. הא
בצינעה הא בפרהסיא. Ha b'tzina ha b'farhesia. Maybe that was in private
and therefore it wasn't a קידוש השם, Kiddush Hashem, an issue of
קידוש השם, Kiddush Hashem, but had it been in public, it would
have been an issue of קידוש השם. Kiddush Hashem. Now, what does
it mean it was in private? The king goes to the בית
עבודה זרה beis avodah zarah and that's in private? So רש"י Rashi
says, well, the definition of public you'll remember was in the presence
of ten Jews. Right. So were we to say there's an act
of קידוש השם Kiddush Hashem by non-Jews, it would only mean that
they would have to do it, not do an עבירה aveira if
their life is at stake or whatever, in the presence of ten
Jews. Which is completely bizarre, right? That their act of קידוש השם
Kiddush Hashem means that they shouldn't transgress the שבע מצוות בני נח
sheva mitzvos b'nei Noach in the presence of ten Jews, but in
public amongst non-Jews, it wouldn't be an act of קידוש השם. Kiddush
Hashem. So that's very strange. Anyway, but that's the way רש"י Rashi
reads it. תוספות Tosafos does not disagree, but תוספות Tosafos says it
sounds like when the גמרא Gemara says מה הוה עלה, mai hava
alah, it sounds like it's going to come to a conclusion. Read
this way, we're leaving it as an open question. Is this a
proof that there's a problem of קידוש השם Kiddush Hashem by non-Jews
or not? Well, you don't know. It sounded like there wasn't the
problem, but in the end maybe it was just an issue of
private so you don't really know. תוספות Tosafos says no, he has
a different גירסא girsa of the גמרא. Gemara. His גירסא girsa of
the גמרא Gemara is ואי לא, v'ei lo, if there were ואי
איתא v'im issa if there were a problem of, you know, of
what do you call it? of קידוש השם, Kiddush Hashem, so לימא
ליה leima lei wait a minute, let me see what the גירסא
girsa is, ואי איתא לימא
ליה הא בצינעה הא בפרהסיא. v'im issa leima lei ha b'tzina ha
b'farhesia. So if it were a problem, why didn't אלישע Elisha say
to נעמן, Naaman, hey, that's okay if you do it in private,
but don't do it in public? Meaning that the point is since
אלישע Elisha just gave נעמן Naaman his blanket blessing, right, it seems
like he's saying okay, that's all right, whether it's private or public,
whatever, it's not a problem, געזונטערהייט, gezuntheit, there's not an issue of
קידוש השם. Kiddush Hashem. So according to תוספות, Tosafos, the conclusion of
the גמרא Gemara is that there's not a problem of קידוש השם
Kiddush Hashem by non-Jews. According to רש"י Rashi there is a problem,
but ironically it's defined as when it's in the public, meaning amongst
ten Jews, which is pretty bizarre. But the other thing that I
should point out that is strange is, if you remember from the
previous discussion, קידוש השם Kiddush Hashem amongst Jews was only defined as
the combination of פרהסיא farhesia and when they're trying to make you
transgress, not פרהסיא להנאת עצמו. farhesia la'hanas atzmo. This is a perfect
case of הנאת עצמו. hanas atzmo. So it's a little bit strange
that the גמרא Gemara thinks that this is a scenario of קידוש
השם, Kiddush Hashem, right? Because there's no aspect of הנאת עצמו. hanas
atzmo. Maybe it thinks that it's asking specifically because it's עבודה זרה.
avodah zarah. But again, from the עבודה זרה avodah zarah perspective, it's
not real עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, it just looks like עבודה זרה.
avodah zarah. So it's a little bit strange why the גמרא Gemara
thinks that this is considered an issue of קידוש השם Kiddush Hashem
all together. Okay, and anyway, so we either answer or don't answer
the question of קידוש השם Kiddush Hashem by non-Jews. Now the גמרא
Gemara continues, ends up this discussion about giving up your life. אמר
רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, מעשה באדם אחד,
maaseh b'adam echad, a story with a certain man, שנתן עיניו באשה
אחת, shenasan einav b'isha achas, that he had a lust after a
particular woman, והעלה לבו טינא, v'haalah libo tina, I'm okay his eyes
were looking at a certain woman and his heart was filled with
lust, he had this like uncontrollable lust for this woman, ובאו ושאלו
לרופאים, u'bau v'shaalu l'rofim, and they asked the doctors what should we
do, this guy's going crazy, ואמרו אין לו תקנה עד שתבעל, v'amru
ein lo takana ad shetibael, the only way he's going to sort
of be cured from this is if he actually has intercourse with
this woman. אמרו חכמים ימות ואל תבעל לו, Amru chachamim yamis v'al
tibael lo, we'd rather he should die than have intercourse with him.
So then they said, all right, תעמוד לפניו ערומה, taamod l'fanav aruma,
maybe it'll work if she just stands naked in front of him,
that'll do something to satisfy his lust. Is she married? Well, we're
going to get to that. ימות ואל תעמוד לפניו ערומה, Yamus v'al
taamod l'fanav aruma, so the rabbis say sorry, he has to die
rather than doing that. תספר עמו מאחורי הגדר. tesaper immo me'achorei hageder.
Let them just have like a conversation and she'll be behind the
wall. I guess the idea behind the wall is so we're not
afraid that he'll attack her as a result, she'll be protected, you
know, but maybe, I don't know, was it a sexual conversation or
just סתם stam to talk? Anyway, so they said, ימות ואל תספר
עמו מאחורי הגדר. yamus ve'al tesaper immo me'achorei hageder. No, better he
should die. Okay, so that's an interesting end to this whole discussion.
How does that fit into the parameters of what we've been talking
about? פליגי בה רב יצחק בר אידי ורבי שמואל בר נחמני. Pligi
bah Rav Yitzchak bar Idi ve'Rabbi Shmuel bar Nachmani. So they debated
it. חד אמר אשת איש הייתה, Chad amar eishet ish hayeta, she
was a married woman, וחד אמר פנויה הייתה, ve'chad amar pnuyah hayeta,
she was unmarried. בשלמא למאן דאמר אשת איש הייתה, Bishlama leman de'amar
eishet ish hayeta,
if you say she was married it makes sense, שפיר. shapir. Now,
does it really make sense? We'll get back to that. But let's
finish the discussion. אלא למאן דאמר פנויה הייתה, Ela leman de'amar pnuyah
hayeta, if you say she was single, מאי כולי האי, mai kulei
hai, why so many, why go so overboard? I mean, his life
is at stake at least according to what the doctors say. רב
פפא אמר משום פגם משפחה. Rav Pappa amar mishum pgam mishpacha.
Well,
it's true, but we're doing it to save the family from the
embarrassment, like now it's interesting, you might remember before, right, that the
whole discussion about saving somebody who's running after a woman to, you
know, to rape her or whatever, we would intervene, and one of
the explanations was not just to save her from the act of
assault and rape, but also because of the פגם pgam that would
result from it. But there פגם pgam was limited to a case
when it was a forbidden, you know, when it was an actually
forbidden act of intercourse and weightily forbidden, חייב כרת chayav kares or
חייב מיתה. chayav misa. Here you don't have that. She's a פנויה.
pnuyah. We're not assuming even that she's a נידה. niddah. So it
says okay, but there's still an aspect of פגם, pgam, the פגם
pgam of the family. It's funny, like and she's not נפגמה nifgama
at all through this? Okay, so which is strange, but anyway,
so but somehow, you're right, from the act of הלכות halachos of
יהרג ואל יעבור yehareg ve'al ya'avor and those types of things it's
not an issue, but we have to protect the honor of the
family. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, which would presumably be even
in just talking from behind the fence. So the גמרא Gemara says,
רבא אמר משום פגם משפחה ורב אחא בריה דרב איקא אמר כדי
שלא יהיו בנות ישראל פרוצות בעריות. Rava amar mishum pgam mishpacha ve'Rav
Acha birei de'Rav Ika amar kedei shelo yiheyu bnot Yisrael prutzos ba'arayos.
It's not just to protect the family,
like let's imagine a case, I don't know, that she didn't have
a family and that she was willing to go along with it
or something of that. No, it's almost like for societal purposes, we
cannot go ahead and give a license to this type of behavior.
Somebody, some man says they're lusting after a woman and then we're
going to allow, you know, these types of behaviors, right? So we
have to ensure this and do this
to protect the Jewish women from being sort of, you know, persuaded
to do acts that are inappropriate
and for us to tolerate those things. So the גמרא Gemara says,
ולינסבה מינסב, v'linsba minsav, so why not just get married if she
was single? Of course it doesn't ask what she thought about it.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says,
לא מייתבא דעתיה, lo miyasva da'ateih, no, that wouldn't have worked. Okay,
maybe that would have been a solution in theory, but it wouldn't
solve his like his lust, his now illness which was born out
of his lust. כדרבי יצחק, ki'd'Rabbi Yitzchak, like רבי יצחק Rabbi Yitzchak
says, דאמר רבי יצחק מיום שחרב בית המקדש ניטל טעם ביאה וניתנה
לעוברי עבירה. d'amar Rabbi Yitzchak miyom shecharav Beit HaMikdash nital ta'am biyah
venitnah le'ovrei aveirah. From the day the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash was
destroyed, the satisfaction that comes through intercourse was sort of taken away
and given to only people who are doing sinful intercourse. There's greater
satisfaction in transgressing or pleasure, guilty pleasure. שנאמר מים גנובים ימתקו ולחם
סתרים ינעם. shene'emar mayim gnuvim yimtaku v'lechem setarim yinam.
Stolen waters will be sweet and bread of, you know, of hidden
bread will be tasty. So bread also is often a metaphor for
sexual intercourse. Now,
this is a very strange גמרא, Gemara, well not strange, but it's
a גמרא Gemara that needs to be grappled with because the גמרא
Gemara says like, okay, the end answers one way or another it's
saying fine, according to הלכה halacha it's really not a problem, but
you know, we can't just allow this type of behavior. We as
the rabbis have to safeguard women or society or protect their families
or whatever the case might be and therefore we can't tolerate this.
Okay. Also, you know, and especially you understand that part of the
issue is that it's not like somebody's holding a gun to this
man's head, right? The guy is having this like lust, you know,
this self-reported lust, so one wonders how much that like sort of
changes, you know, the issue. Then the person is actually, it's generated
from within him, he himself is asking to do this type of
a thing, right? Like I one wonders, if somebody was holding a
gun to his head and says we want you to speak to,
you know, stand, you know, we want you to look at this
woman when she's standing in front of you naked, right, would we
have said no, you have to let the guy pull the trigger
and kill him? Maybe we would, maybe we wouldn't, but it's a
very different type of a question, right, as opposed to when it's
the person himself who's like generating it and what that does to
open up the gates of allowing people to like, you know, sort
of whet and act on their, you know, sort of sexual desires.
So, so that's at least the second answer is clear that it's
about protect, you know, not tolerating this in terms of society and
so on, not an actual technical הלכה. halacha. But how about the
first answer, that it says she was married? If she's married, we
understand it. Now, do we understand it because of the הלכות halachos
about יהרג ואל יעבור? yehareg ve'al ya'avor? But what... Wait a minute,
this isn't an actual forbidden act of
intercourse. The first thing was, but then they said let her stand
naked, let her talk behind the fence. So some ראשונים rishonim derive
from here the principle that when we say יהרג ואל יעבור yeihareg
ve'al ya'avor for the big three, it doesn't just include the act
itself, it includes אביזריהו. avizraihu. That's what we said before, that word
before of appurtenances. So even though it's not the actual act of
forbidden adultery, but because it's connected to it, it's some form of
sexually exciting sort of encounter, so that actually would also be יהרג
ואל יעבור. yeihareg ve'al ya'avor. That also, by the way, might work
before in the earlier discussion about נעמן Na'aman and bending down, and
even though it wasn't really עבודה זרה, avoda zara, someone even goes
say maybe מראית עין maris ayin of the big three is יהרג
ואל יעבור, yeihareg ve'al ya'avor, right? What?
יחוד yichud or something?
יחוד, yichud, right, would יחוד yichud be יהרג ואל יעבור? yeihareg ve'al
ya'avor? יחוד yichud isn't even מראית עין, maris ayin, יחוד yichud is
considered it might lead to it, right? So then their questions are,
what if it's דאורייתא de'oraisa but not the actual weighty sin itself?
What if it's דרבנן derabbanan but it's connected to it? What if
it's about just a מראית עין maris ayin of the big three?
It looks like it. I'm going to bend down in front of
the idol, pick up my wallet that fell down. Okay? That's completely
not עבודה זרה, avoda zara, but you think I'm doing עבודה זרה,
avoda zara, right? So then it expands this huge way about when
you say יהרג ואל יעבור. yeihareg ve'al ya'avor. And you get people
asking שאלות shailos like is it יהרג ואל יעבור yeihareg ve'al ya'avor
to go mixed swimming? I'm serious, right, not as a joke, right?
It's אביזריהו avizraihu of
גילוי עריות, giluy arayos, people are not fully clothed, you have sexual
thoughts, married women, whatever the case might be. Okay, so that's one
way that you could sort of take from this if you think
the question of אשת איש eishess ish means that it's because it
was the big, was considered יהרג ואל יעבור. yeihareg ve'al ya'avor. Others
say no. What the גמרא gemara meant is we understand if she
was married, not why it's יהרג ואל יעבור, yeihareg ve'al ya'avor, but
why of course the rabbis wouldn't allow it, right? How could we,
how could we tolerate, I mean from a rabbinic protecting of women,
marriage, society allow a man, allow a married woman to stand naked
before another man, right? So it's not because it would be יהרג
ואל יעבור, yeihareg ve'al ya'avor, it's just it would be obvious why
we couldn't allow it, but if she was single we have a
harder time understanding it and then it says no, even there we're
going to allow it. Okay, so this end סוגיא sugya certainly leads
to a lot of fascinating discussion. What?
Even there they prohibited it.
Right, we prohibit it. We prohibit it, but not because of יהרג
ואל יעבור. yeihareg ve'al ya'avor. Yes, Charlie.
The Arabian Nights are full of lovesickness stories. Really? That usually end
up with a couple getting together and society approving. So this might
have been a way of making it distinct from the, this
was way before the Arabian Nights.
Some stories are ancient?
That's interesting. Hmm, yes.
What do we think about this פרק perek ending with a forbidden
fruit thing?
That's interesting.
I don't know, I feel like it's fun to think about what
that, how the end of the פרק perek ends with, right, a
whole פרק perek about...
It's an interesting question like thinking about the fact that בן סורר
ומורה ben sorer umoreh sort of starts with the idea about על
שם סופו al shem sofo and where something will lead and maybe
here also there's an aspect of it like taking extra precautions, precautions,
that wasn't what you were saying about the last line, but thinking
in that term, taking extra precautions about protecting society the same way
בן סורר ומורה ben sorer umoreh is protecting society. Maybe this act
itself is not so intrinsically horrific, but the question is what would
be the implications if, so I'm just tying it to the beginning
of בן סורר ומורה. ben sorer umoreh. What thought do you have
about that?
I don't know, I just, maybe the way we raise people and
the boundaries we put and remembering that, right,
sometimes boundaries make things tempting. Right, interesting, interesting. All right, give it
some thought. Okay, הדרן על בן סורר ומורה. hadran al ben sorer
umoreh. Now you see why people learn this פרק, perek, it's a
lot of fun. All right, moving right on to the next פרק.
perek. Okay, so that was the end of the people that get
סקילה, sekilah, of which בן סורר ומורה ben sorer umoreh was one,
and that allowed us to talk about בן סורר ומורה ben sorer
umoreh and allowed us to talk about יהרג ואל יעבור yeihareg ve'al
ya'avor and about בא במחתרת ba bamachteres and all those fun cases.
Okay, ואלו הנשרפין. ve'eilu hanisrafin. Back to the list of who gets
which מיתות. misos. So we go from סקילה sekilah to שריפה, sereifah,
right? We all remember that from יום כיפור, yom kippur, right? Did
anybody notice the order? סקילה, שריפה, הרג, חנק sekilah, sereifah, herig, chenek
when you were doing the וידוי. vidui. Okay, ואלו הנשרפין. ve'eilu hanisrafin.
Now you know which way we פוסק pasken about those debates. Okay,
ואלו הנשרפין. ve'eilu hanisrafin. The following people get
שריפה. sereifah. הבא על אשה ובתה. haba al isha uvittah. Not a
long list. A man who has intercourse with a woman and her
daughter. Now as we'll find out in the גמרא, gemara, the case
that's explicit in the תורה torah is a man who has intercourse
with his mother-in-law. Okay, but that is called, but a mother-in-law if
you think about it is a woman and her daughter. So that's
also going to get translated into his wife's daughter and then we're
going to also discuss his own daughter and so on. Okay, ובת
כהן, uvat kohen, and also the ובת כהן uvat kohen שזינתה. shezinisah.
Also the ובת כהן uvat kohen who fornicates, and if you might
remember there's a big debate, which case of the
ובת כהן, uvat kohen, ארוסה, נשואה, arusah, nesuah, etc., whatever, some case
of the ובת כהן uvat kohen she gets שריפה. sereifah. Now...
יש בכלל אשה ובתה yesh bikhlal ishah u-vittah included in the אשה
ובתה ishah u-vittah
is
the following cases: בתו bitto his own daughter, ובת בתו, ובת בנו
u-vat bitto u-vat bino and his own granddaughter. Now that's his own
daughter and granddaughter even if it's not his wife's daughter, okay, if
it's through a if it's through a sexual relationship that was not
marriage. So he could have a daughter who's not his wife's daughter
or a granddaughter. So that's also gets שרפה, sereifah, okay,
ובת אשתו u-vat ishto his wife's daughter even if it's not his,
his stepdaughter, okay, ובת בתו u-vat bitto, ובת בנו u-vat bino and
his grand-stepdaughter, his
whatever that is, his step-granddaughter, okay,
okay,
חמותו hamoto now, the case that's in the תורה Torah of שרפה,
sereifah, it's his mother-in-law, ואם חמותו v'em hamoto his
grandmother-in-law, ואם חמיו v'em hamiv or his grandmother-in-law on his father's side,
okay? So you got all those? Okay, so those are the cases.
Now so now let's just start with the פסוקים pesukim in the
תורה, Torah, okay? The פסוקים pesukim in the תורה Torah is wait
I have a חומש humash
here. Okay
so give you the פסוקים pesukim here.
יח יז Yud Het Yud Zayin says wait wait wait one of
the time, one of the time. יח יז Yud Het Yud Zayin
is ערבת אשה ובתה לא תגלה, ervat ishah u-vittah lo tegaleh, okay,
את בת בנה ואת בת בתה לא תקח לגלות ערבתה שארה הנה
זמה היא. et bat binah v'et bat bittah lo tikkah l'galot ervatah
she'erah henmah zimah hi. So that is the case of
wife's daughter and granddaughter, okay? So what is that?
ערבת ervat one minute. Okay here's wife
daughter
and granddaughter, okay? So that's even if it's not his. So that's
ערבת אשה ובתה, ervat ishah u-vittah, okay, לא תגלה את בת בנה
ואת בת בתה
לא תקח לגלות ערבתה
שאר המה זמה היא.
lo tegaleh et bat binah v'et bat bittah lo tikkah l'galot
ervatah she'er hemah
zimah hi.
Fine,
זמה היא. זמה היא Zima hi zima hi. is going to be
an important word. Okay so that's one. What's the next פסוק? pasuk?
What's the other
פסוק? pasuk?
כ יד. Kaf Yud Dalet. ואיש אשר
יקח את אשה ואת אמה, v'ish
asher yikkah et ishah
v'et immah, okay, so that's let's use a different color.
The mother that's חמותו, hamoto, okay, ואיש אשר יקח את אשה ואת
אמה זמה
היא באש ישרפו אתו ואתהן.
v'ish asher yikkah et ishah
v'et immah zimah hi ba'esh yisrefu oto v'etahen. Okay so זמה היא,
zimah hi. so there's the זמה היא zimah hi and it's באש
ישרפו. ba'esh yisrefu. Now notice here you have the punishment, here you
have the negative
לא תגלה lo tegaleh forgot the word לא תגלה. lo tegaleh. Here
you have the prohibition
and here you have the punishment. So what we're going to have
to do is we're going to have to say how do you
know what's punished here? That's by fire, that's we're going to connect
going up a generation to going down a generation and so on.
Okay? So a wife and her mother and a wife her daughter
they're both going to be by fire. How do you know this
is prohibited? We're going to you know we're going to apply the
prohibition up here and the punishment down here. We're going to connect
the two. Okay? So that's in terms of wife's daughter granddaughter and
wife's mother and we're going to figure out how to include grandmother.
Now how do you know about a man's a man's own daughter?
So that's a פסוק, pasuk, you have the next פסוק, pasuk, it
is where is it?
What?
Twenty four fourteen? יח י. Yud Het Yud. Yes thank you.
ערבת בת
בנך או בת בתך לא תגלה ערבתן כי ערבתך הנה.
ervat bat binkha o vat bittkha
lo
tegaleh ervatan ki ervatkha henmah. Okay? So that's your, I wish I
had a better working one here
I
wanted a different color. Let's see if I got one up by
my thing.
There's something here. Okay.
Yes.
Okay. ערבת בת ervat bat now interestingly, okay, it only mentions by
the way it can be son's daughter as well. It only mentions
granddaughter, okay? It says ערבת בת בנך או בת בתך, ervat bat
binkha o vat bittkha, oops בנך או בת בתך לא תגלה ערבתן
כי ערבתך הנה.
binkha o vat bittkha lo
tegaleh ervatan ki ervatkha henmah. It skips over
בת. bat. It skips over בת. bat. Okay we're going to sort
of figure that out to get by a קל וחומר, kal va-homer,
anyway. לא תגלה ערוותן. lo tegaleh ervatan. So here is what we're
going to have to do, okay? כי ערוותך הנה. ki ervat-cha hena.
The הנה's hena going to be important later. כי ערוותך הנה. ki
ervat-cha hena. So what what we're going to have to do, worry
about that later, okay? Is first of all, here we're going to
have to figure out how do you go up another generation? How
do you connect the, this gives the punishment, this gives the prohibition?
That'll be easy enough, sort of. Then we're going to have to
figure out here, how do you get the punishment and how do
you also include, right, the daughter? You know, because we just started
with the granddaughter. So that's how we're going to have to fill
out everything, okay?
No, I don't think so. Okay. So, alright, let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara. Her prohibition. הבא על אשה שנשא בתה לא
קתני. Ha'ba al isha she'nasa bita lo ktani.
So the משנה Mishnah says, as if, the משנה Mishnah says the
core case is אשה ובתה. isha u'bita. And we're going to include
in אשה ובתה isha u'bita all of these cases. So the core
case of שריפה sreifa should have been the case of mother-in-law, because
that's the case in the תורה. Torah. But the גמרא Gemara is
saying that's not what it says explicitly. הבא על אשה שנשא בתה
לא קתני, Ha'ba al isha she'nasa bita lo ktani, doesn't say a
man who has intercourse with a woman whose daughter he has married,
that would be the case in the תורה, Torah, the mother-in-law. אלא
הבא על אשה ובתה. Ela ha'ba al isha u'bita.
It sounds like mother and daughter, unrelated to the fact that you're
married to the woman. מכלל דתרווייהו איסורא. Miklal d'trivaihu isura. So it
sounds like what we're talking about is two cases in which that
can be mother-in-law. What does that mean two cases that can be
mother-in-law? You're not married to either of them. So what we're saying
is you're married to this one, and הבא על אשה ובתה. ha'ba
al isha u'bita.
That if you go ahead and have intercourse with either the grandmother-in-law,
that's the אשה, isha, or her daughter, or your mother-in-law, that would
be a case of the explicit biblical prohibition. Okay, that's how we're
reading it, right? Because it doesn't say, we know we have to
start with the biblical case of mother-in-law. That's the only case it
explicitly says שריפה. sreifa. But it doesn't say you're married to either
of the women in the משנה. Mishnah. So the only cases of
mother-in-law that you're not married to either of the women is we're
talking about your grandmother-in-law, that's the אשה, isha, or her daughter, or
your mother-in-law. Meaning,
why don't we just say that that means an abstract category? Right.
So the גמרא's Gemara understanding that the משנה Mishnah is starting with
the idea of the concrete case in the תורה Torah and then
broadening it, not like, it's not starting with an abstraction. I understand
how you want to read it. Okay, but that's at least the
assumption the גמרא's Gemara working with. ומני הוא, U'manee hu, what would
that be? חמותו ואם חמותו. Chamoto v'em chamoto.
And it's saying like starting from this concrete case, the other things
are included. מכלל דתרווייהו כתיבי בהדיא. Miklal d'trivaihu ksivi b'hedya. It sounds
like the first case in the משנה Mishnah meant these are the
explicit cases in the תורה Torah of שריפה, sreifa, and the rest
are included. ואידך מדרשה אתיא, V'idach midrasha atya, the rest are going
to be included by a דרשה. drasha. הני, Hanee, so that means
that the case we're going to assume the case in the תורה
Torah is not just mother-in-law but grandmother-in-law. הני כאביי דאמר משמע דתרתי
מביניהו. Hanee k'Abaye d'amar mashma d'tartei mibeneihu. מתניתין מני רבי עקיבא. Masnisin
mane Rabbi Akiva.
So we're going to have a whole issue later, which we're not
going to unpack now, but in way of understanding a certain debate,
and according to אביי, Abaye, within that debate, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
will say that in the תורה Torah it's implicit that the grandmother-in-law
also gets שריפה. sreifa. Okay, so according to רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva
that way of reading רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, the משנה Mishnah could
say these two are the cases in the תורה, Torah, because he
thinks grandmother-in-law is in the תורה. Torah. אלא רבא דאמר חמותו אחר
מיתה איכא בינייהו, Ela Rava d'amar chamoto achar misa ika beneihu, but
according to רבא Rava that says that they're really debating over there,
later we'll see, the question about is mother-in-law still prohibited after the
wife dies? Okay, and nobody though says that grandmother-in-law is in the
פסוקים. psukim. All right, so according to that approach that nobody says
grandmother-in-law is in the פסוקים, psukim, מתניתין מני, masnisin mane, who's our
משנה Mishnah going like? So אמר לך רבא, amar lach Rava, תניא
הבא על אשה שנשא בתה. tanya ha'ba al isha she'nasa bita. Fine,
when it says mother and a daughter, it means a mother whose
daughter you have married. Just read the משנה Mishnah that אשה ובתה
isha u'bita in the משנה Mishnah means your wife and her mother.
That's what it means. It means the concrete case of mother-in-law. Don't
read it in this fancy way that it means mother-in-law and grandmother-in-law.
Okay? So that was just the first line in the משנה. Mishnah.
We want to get the first case in the משנה Mishnah not
like Jenna said an abstraction, we want it to be a concrete
case in the תורה Torah of mother-in-law, which is the explicit case
in the תורה Torah of שריפה. sreifa. Now we're going to have
to worry about all the rest of this board. So let's take
a look. Okay, יש בכל אשה ובתה חמותו ואם חמותו ואם חמיו.
Yesh b'chol isha u'bita chamoto v'em chamoto v'em chamiv.
So the first thing we say is included in this first case
is, you know, dot dot dot the end of the משנה Mishnah
is mother-in-law and grandmother-in-law. So לאביי, l'Abaye, so remember אביי Abaye said
that the first case in the משנה Mishnah was grandmother-in-law. So what
does the end of the משנה Mishnah mean when it says, oh,
included in this is grandmother-in-law? So לאביי, l'Abaye, איידי דקא בעי למתני
אם חמיו תני נמי חמותו ואם חמותו. aidee d'ka baee l'misnee em
chamiv, tanee namee chamoto v'em chamoto. You're right. According to אביי Abaye
the only thing the end of the משנה Mishnah including is grandmother-in-law
on the father's side. Grandmother-in-law on the mother's side, right, is he
thinks is explicit in the פסוקים. pesukim. All right, it's a little
funny because we haven't seen this debate later on. But you got
the point that they're debating whether the first case in the משנה
mishna according to אביי Abaye refers to a grandmother-in-law. And the end
of the משנה mishna says, oh, included in the first case in
the משנה, mishna, it also expands to include grandmother-in-law. But wait, אביי
Abaye said the first case was grandmother-in-law. No, no, no. The first
case was grandmother-in-law on your mother's side. The end of the משנה
mishna is saying and it also includes grandmother-in-law on the father's side.
One minute. Okay.
לרבא איצטריכא ליה למיתני אם חמיו ואם חמותו. Le-Rava itztreicha lei limitni
em chamiv ve-em chamoto. According to רבא, Rava, it's much easier, right?
The end of the משנה mishna is expanding it beyond mother-in-law to
grandmother-in-law on father's side or mother's side. תני נמי חמותו, Tani nami
chamoto, the end of the משנה mishna also mentions mother-in-law, right? You
understand the problem. This works very well with Genaz's theory. The beginning
of the משנה mishna says that a mother and her daughter. And
then the end says, oh, and this also includes mother-in-law and grandmother-in-law.
So what did it refer to initially? So Genaz would say, no,
initially we're just talking about an abstraction and then we're listing the
specifics. Okay, but the גמרא Gemara is saying initially we're talking about
the concrete case in the תורה. Torah. So if the concrete case
in the תורה Torah is mother-in-law, what do you mean at the
end when you say, oh, this includes mother-in-law? So the point is,
no, no, no. Of course, some of it was already included. Mother-in-law
or grandmother-in-law on one side, but we're saying it includes all the
cases related to mother-in-law, even grandmother-in-law, even grandmother-in-law on the father's side
and so on. Okay? יישר כוח. Yasher koach. You had a great...
It sounds like they get to the same place but through different
logic.
Well, they're correct, although there is a question whether grandmother-in-law is explicit
in the פסוקים pesukim or not. But it doesn't matter. Right now
we're just parsing the משנה. mishna. Okay, now we're done with parsing
the משנה mishna and now we're going to get to figuring out
how all of these are included. Okay? Because this is the only
case that's explicit in the תורה Torah that gets שריפה. sreifa. All
right? The other things are explicit... these are explicit that they're forbidden,
okay, but this is the only one... see, that's why I did
it in red. That's the only one that's explicit that it gets
שריפה. sreifa. Okay. All right, so it says like this. Now, מנא
הני מילי? Mena hanei milei? Where do you get this from to
expand it to all these cases? דתנו רבנן, Detanu rabanan, we taught:
אשה אשר יקח את אשה ואת אמה, Isha asher yikach et isha
ve-et imah, if a man takes a woman and her mother. אין
לי אלא אשה ואמה בת אשה ובת בתה ובת בנה מנין? Ein
li ela isha ve-imah bat isha u-vat bitah u-vat binah minayin?
How do you know that all these cases which are forbidden, how
do you know they also get שריפה, sreifa, the
daughters? מנין? Minayin? Wait,
I just lost my page. ובת בנה ובת בתה מנין? u-vat binah
u-vat bitah minayin? נאמר כאן זמה ונאמר להלן זמה. Ne'emar kan zima
ve-ne'emar le-halan zima. Ah, זמה היא zimah hi, זמה היא. zimah hi
So that's going to be great. That's going to allow us a
lot of application here. Okay? מה להלן בתה ובת בתה ובת בנה
אף כאן בתה ובת בתה ובת בנה. Mah le-halan bitah u-vat bitah
u-vat binah af kan bitah u-vat bitah u-vat binah. Okay,
so the same way over
there, wait, does that make sense? ונאמר להלן זמה. ve-ne'emar le-halan zima.
מה להלן בתה ובת בתה ובת בנה. Mah le-halan bitah u-vat bitah
u-vat binah.
The same way I guess it means that all these are forbidden.
It's a little funny להלן le-halan and כאן. kan. Yeah, but that's
what רש״י Rashi says. The same way they're forbidden, daughter and granddaughter,
so when it comes to the punishment, we're also going to say
daughter and granddaughter. So the זמה היא zima hi is going to
allow us... this זמה היא zima hi is going to allow us
to say שריפה. sreifa. Okay? So that's how we're going to... how
we're going to get those to be בשריפה. be-sreifa.
Okay. מנין לעשות זכרים כנקבות? Minayin la'asot zecharim ki-nekevot?
How do you know to make men like women? Whatever that means,
we'll see in the גמרא. Gemara. נאמר כאן זמה ונאמר להלן זמה,
Ne'emar kan zima ve-ne'emar le-halan zima, because of זמה. zima. מה להלן
זכרים כנקבות אף כאן זכרים כנקבות. Mah le-halan zecharim ki-nekevot af kan
zecharim ki-nekevot. So the גמרא Gemara is going to try to figure
out what that means. It's not clear at all what that means.
מנין לעשות למטה כלמעלה? Minayin la'asot lemata ke-lemala? How do you know
to make something below like the thing above?
נאמר כאן זמה ונאמר להלן זמה. Ne'emar kan zima ve-ne'emar le-halan zima.
מה להלן למטה כלמעלה אף כאן למטה כלמעלה. Mah le-halan lemata ke-lemala
af kan lemata ke-lemala. Very cryptic. The whole rest of the עמוד
amud is going to be figuring out this male-female and below and
above thing. ומה כאן למעלה כלמטה, u-mah kan lemala ke-lemata, and then
the same way there above is like below, אף כאן למעלה כלמטה,
af kan lemala ke-lemata, here too above is like below. So the
end of this ברייתא braita doesn't seem to make any sense. But
somehow we're going to interpret it in a way to get in
everything here. So let's take a look. Okay? אמר מר. Amar mar.
מנין לעשות זכרים כנקבות? Minayin la'asot zecharim ki-nekevot?
So מה זכרים כנקבות? mah zecharim ki-nekevot? What do you mean make
the males like the females? אילימא בת בנה כבת בתה? Ilima bat
binah ke-bat bitah? So if you mean that the granddaughter of the
daughter and the granddaughter of the son have the same status? Okay,
these granddaughters are the same, right? They're equally forbidden. So that's explicit
in the פסוק, pasuk, right? It says בת בנה ובת בתה. bat
binah u-vat bitah. So you don't need a פסוק pasuk for that.
Okay, so אילימא בת בנה כבת בתה בהדיא כתיבי. ilima bat binah
ke-bat bitah be-hedya ketivi.
They're both explicit in the פסוק, pasuk, and in terms of getting
שריפה, sreifa, they're both included at the same time since they're in
this פסוק pasuk and we apply שריפה sreifa here. So we don't
need something else to say granddaughter through the daughter or granddaughter through
the son is the same thing. Okay, so אלא אם חמיו כאם
חמותו. ela eim chamiv ke'eim chamoto.
Ah, what we mean is how do you know that not only
is forbidden is your grandmother on your mother's side? On your wife's
mother's side? But also your grandmother on your wife's father's side? Okay,
that's אם חמיו ואם חמותו. eim chamiv ve'eim chamoto. How do we
know that that this that these great you know whatever grandmothers-in-law have
the same the
are the same? Okay, so that's a reasonable question.
So the גמרא Gemara says אשתא אם חמותו לא קאמר לן אם
חמיו מהדר ליה? hashta eim chamoto lo ka'amar lan eim chamiv mehader
lei?
But we haven't even proven grandmother-in-law. The פסוקים psukim don't talk about
grandmother. So we wouldn't be jumping to talk about grandmother on the
mother's side father's side versus mother's side. We would first have to
establish that grandmother is forbidden. All right, so that can't be male
and female because we haven't established that yet. So אמר אביי, amar
Abaye, so we now turn the עמוד. amud. So אביי Abaye says
הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar, this is what it means.
מניין לעשות שאר הבא ממנו כשאר הבא ממנה. minayin la'asot she'er haba
mimenu keshe'er haba mimena. So the זכרים ונקבות zecharim unekevot here are
talking about husband and wife. We know that her daughter granddaughters right
are forbidden and get שריפה. sreifa. How do we know that his
daughter and granddaughters? We know they're forbidden. How do we know they
get שריפה? sreifa? That's a good question right? Because all of those
were included in the משנה. Mishna. So we've got these getting שריפה.
sreifa. We've got these getting שריפה. sreifa. How do we know these
get שריפה? sreifa? So that's the זכרים כנקבות zecharim kenekevot meaning descendants
of the man are like descendants of the woman. These apply to
his wife's daughters whether they're his kids or not. What about when
they're his kids but they're not his wife but but he never
married their mother? Okay. This seems common sense.
I mean it seems so related to the...
Yes I agree but there's a general principle אין עונשין מן הדין
ein onshin min hadin and so on. Right. And conceptually also it
is different. Right? I mean when the פסוק pasuk says אשה ובתה,
isha uvita, right? There's a sense of like the two women are
like related to one another right? Whereas this is conceptually different. This
is your related to the woman that you're you know you the
man are related to the woman you're having intercourse with as opposed
to the two women are connected. So how do you know that
these we know they're prohibited but how do you know to apply
שריפה sreifa to them? That's a good question. That's part of what
we have to do. Right? We've got we know that's part of
what you know what we're out here to prove. Okay. So it
says
נאמר כאן זימה ונאמר להלן זימה. ne'emar kan zima vene'emar lehalan zima.
Oh because it says זימה zima here or here whatever and it
says זימה zima here. The problem is the גמרא Gemara and therefore
we apply שריפה sreifa the same way it said זימה zima here
we applied שריפה. sreifa. It says זימה zima here and we apply
שריפה. sreifa. But the גמרא Gemara says one minute the גמרא Gemara
says נאמר כאן זימה ונאמר להלן זימה ne'emar kan zima vene'emar lehalan
zima ובהאי שאר דידיה לא כתיב ביה זימה. uv'hai she'er didei lo
ktiv bei zima. There's only a little problem. It doesn't say זימה
zima here. So you're saying we're going to get שריפה sreifa because
of the word זימה zima but there's no word זימה zima here.
So אמר רבא אמר לי רב יצחק בר אבדימי אתיא הנה הנה
אתיא זימה זימה. amar Rava amar li Rav Yitzchak bar Avdimi atya
hena hena atya zima zima. No but it does say הנה hena
here כי שארך הנה ki she'ercha hena and in another פסוק pasuk
completely unrelated to this it says what did it say? What's the
word where it says הנה hena and זימה? zima? What's the word
it says?
What? י"ח י"ז? yud-chet yud-zayin?
Yeah we read it yesterday.
Yeah but
it's not somebody's not paying attention. But it might be but it's
not a פסוק pasuk related to any of this. It's just some
random some פסוק pasuk that has both of those keywords in it.
Every no that doesn't say הנה. hena. Oh no it does you're
right שארה הנה זימה היא. she'era hena zima hi. I'm sorry I
apologize it is related to this. Okay this פסוק pasuk says I
cut it out I should have had it here. Sorry. Okay שארה
הנה. she'era hena. So my mistake I'm sorry שארה הנה. she'era hena.
It does say both keywords there okay זימה היא. zima hi. So
so yeah so you're right. It says when it says זימה זימה
zima zima it means from this we get זימה היא zima hi
and from the הנה הנה hena hena we apply it from here
to here. Okay you got it? So the זימה zima here got
us to do שריפה sreifa here and the הנה hena link gets
us to now apply take it the next step further and apply
שריפה sreifa to this case. All right? So it says it says
זימה zima but it doesn't really mean זימה. zima. It says the
זימה דרשה zima drasha carries over. All right? So that's how we've
got these get שריפה sreifa and these get
שריפה. sreifa. אתיא הנה הנה אתיא זימה זימה. atya hena hena atya
zima zima. אמר מר. amar mar. Good that was a good read
of the ברייתא braita the זכרים כנקבות zecharim kenekevot and it got
us done one of the things we needed to know how to
get to we needed to get done which is to get שריפה
sreifa to that case. Okay אמר מר מניין לעשות למטה כלמעלה. amar
mar minayin la'asot lemata ke'lema'ala. Now we're left with this other strange
phrase in the ברייתא braita above like below.
So מאי למטה כלמעלה? mai lemata ke'lema'ala? What does that mean above
and below? אילימא בת בנה ובת בתה כבתה eillima bat bina u-vat
bitta kevita ובת בנו ובת בתו? u-vat bino u-vat bito? But הדר
קשיא.
hadari
kashya. If you mean
how do we know to apply so above right means a... a
like,
well here, if we're going down this way, right, above is a
closer relation and and and below is a lower relation. So if
it says how do you know to apply
that the granddaughters are like the daughters? So he says, we don't
need a special פסוק pasuk to say granddaughters are like daughters. They're
all in the same פסוק, pasuk, right? בת בנה ובת בתה לא
תקח bat bnah u-bat bta lo tikach etc., they're all they're all
learned out together. We don't need a separate פסוק pasuk to tell
you granddaughters are like her daughters. בת בנה ובת בתה bat bnah
u-bat bta they're all learned out together to get שריפה srefah and
they're all in the same פסוק. pasuk. אלא אם חמיו ואם חמותו
כחמותו. ella em chamiv v'em chamoto k'chamoto. Maybe it means like this,
which is the one thing we really have left to do is
grandmother-in-law. That is the one thing we haven't done yet. Okay, also
his own daughter, but we won't worry about that right now. So
how do you know to apply above, further related to him, like
below, like the one that's sort of like closer to him? Okay,
so how do you know how do you know to apply that?
So the גמרא gemara says, היי למטה כלמעלה, hi lemata k'lemaala, it
shouldn't say how do you know to apply below like above. למעלה
כלמטה איבעי. lemaala k'lemata iba-ei. It should have said how do you
know to apply above like below. Alright, so it's just, yes, we
understand you have to do that, go up a generation, but the
phrase this should be below and this should be above. Okay, so
how so- תף, taf, תני למעלה כלמטה. tani lemaala k'lemata. Fine, reverse
the language in the ברייתא. braita. That's what it means. How do
you know to apply the above case like the below case? To
apply it to the great- to the grandmother-in-law. אי הכי, iy hachi,
so okay fine, that's what it was trying to do, apply it
to the grandmother-in-law. But the ברייתא braita says you learn it from
the word זימה. zimmah. Alright, so where is זימה zimmah being said
by one generation higher that you're going to get? The one generation
higher isn't even mentioned. So, yeah. Okay, good. Okay, so- מימרא כאן
תני memra kan tani fine. אי הכי, iy hachi, נאמר כאן זימה
ונאמר להלן זימה, ne-emar kan zimmah v'ne-emar le-hallan zimmah, ומה התם זימה
לא כתיבא? u-mah hatam zimmah lo ktiva? Wait a minute, the case
of the grandmother-in-law isn't in the פסוקים psukim at all. זימה דלא
כתיבא? zimmah dlo ktiva? Oh, it says זימה zimmah by them. No,
the problem is it doesn't mention it at all, so you can't
say it says זימה. zimmah. So what do you mean you're learning
it out from the word זימה? zimmah? Okay, so that's clearly a
good question, what the heck is going on here? So אמר אביי,
amar Abaye, הכי קאמר. hachi ka-amar. Yes, we are trying to learn
grandmother-in-law, but here's, if I asked you, how would you try to
learn out grandmother-in-law from what we have on the board? What would
be the basis for saying that grandmother-in-law should be prohibited? Go down
an extra generation then
go up.
Exactly, since we know that when it's the wife's descendants it goes
down it goes down two generations, when it's the wife's forebearers it
should also go up two generations. So that's exactly what אביי Abaye
reads into the ברייתא. braita. Okay, let's take a look- the ברייתא.
braita. Okay,
so אמר אביי, amar Abaye, הכי קאמר. hachi ka-amar. מניין לעשות שלוש
דורות למעלה? minayin la-asot shalosh dorot lemaala? How do you know the
phrase is how do you know to make למעלה
כלמטה?
lemaala
k'lemata? So למעלה כלמטה lemaala k'lemata does not mean one generation removed
versus two generations removed. למעלה כלמטה lemaala k'lemata means how do you
know that when you're going up you go up two generations the
same way that when you're going down you go down two generations?
Okay, and that's exactly what we're trying to do is apply it
to the grandmother-in-law. So אמר אביי, amar Abaye, הכי קאמר. hachi ka-amar.
מניין לעשות שלוש דורות למעלה minayin la-asot shalosh dorot lemaala to go
three, it says three because it counts the wife as the first
generation, כשלוש דורות למטה? kishlosh dorot lemata? How do you know to
go up, you know, two more generations the same way when you
go down? נאמר למטה זימה ונאמר למעלה זימה, ne-emar lemata zimmah v'ne-emar
lemaala zimmah, מה למטה שלוש דורות אף למעלה שלוש דורות. mah lemata
shalosh dorot af lemaala shalosh dorot. Now it all works. We got
the זימה-זימה zimmah-zimmah connection, right? These two have the זימה-זימה zimmah-zimmah connection,
so we first use the זימה zimmah to say שריפה srefah here,
but now we're going to use the זימה zimmah here to say
because of the זימה zimmah connection to tell you that you go
up the same way down here here it's two generations, there it's
two generations. Now it works very beautifully. That's the זימה-זימה, zimmah-zimmah, that's
exactly what we needed to do. Okay,
ומה בעונש, u-mah ba-ones, now the one thing we have left to
do, which we didn't do is, we have here the prohibition and
the punishment שריפה srefah based on the זימה. zimmah. Here the prohibition
in the פסוק pasuk and the punishment שריפה srefah based on the
הנה henna link. We have here one שריפה srefah one generation, the
גזירה שווה gzeira shava tells you two generations. The only thing we
don't have here is, we know- how do you know it's prohibited?
And that's going to be finished off by the זימה-זימה zimmah-zimmah connection.
Once the זימה zimmah connection is saying you apply this to that,
the same way this tells you go up a generation, it's going
to say the same way this is prohibited, that's prohibited. It's not
enough that the תורה Torah tells you you get punished, you know.
Yes, we can infer that, but the גמרא'ס Gemara's general principle is
אין עונשין אלא אם כן מזהירין. ein onshin ela im ken mazhirin.
It's not enough if the תורה Torah says a punishment, we have
to have a basis to say here's where it's saying you're not
allowed to do it. Okay, so the saying of it is saying
of it through the גזירה שווה. gzeira shava. Okay, ומה
בעונש עשו למטה כלמעלה lemata kimalah אף באזהרה af beazharah nami עשו
למעלה כלמטה. lemala kilematah The end of the ברייתא, braita, so the
ברייתא braita says how do you know to make above like below,
it means how do you know to make the above two generations
like the below is two generations? And then it says how do
you know to make the below like the above? Anyway, somehow he
says at the end of the ברייתא Baraita saying it is and
also and how do you know to make this prohibited with a
negative prohibition like this is, that's also learned from the זמה זמה.
zimah zimah. Okay. So ומה בעונש אסר למטה כלמעלה Umah beones asar
lematah kimalah the same way when it comes to the punishment, right,
the thing that is below is like the thing above, the same
way this gets שריפה srefah and this gets שריפה, srefah, אף באזהרה
when it comes to the prohibition, נמי אסר למעלה כלמטה, nami asar
lemalah kilematah, the above comes like the below. Okay so he says
that's what the two phrases in the ברייתא Baraita of above and
below is doing. First it's telling you you go up two generations
and then it's telling you this is prohibited as well.
רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar, רב אשי Rav Ashi says another
variation of this, לעולם כדקתני, leolam kidekatni, don't switch around the ברייתא
Baraita which is above and which is below. ומאי למטה למטה באיסור.
Umai lemata lemata beissur. When it says למטה lemata it means less
prohibited. Now all that means is I won't go into trying to
read the whole ברייתא Baraita with him, but what he basically—I mean
not less prohibited, they're equally prohibited. But basically, he just says that
the phrase, right remember we said like the phrase of למטה כלמעלה
lemata kimalah? was like the phrase was wrong because
אביי'ס Abaye's meaning—this should have said if it was comparing this to
this, it should have said, this should have been
למעלה—wait lemala no, I'm
sorry, I gotta remind myself. רב אשי Rav Ashi how does he
read this, hold on one second.
Right, the phrase was, how do you know to do, right right,
he's just really a difference in terminology. How do you know to
make למטה כלמעלה? lemata kimalah Okay, so אביי Abaye reversed it. אביי
Abaye said how do you know to make למעלה, lemala, the
mother-in-law and grandmother-in-law like למטה, lemata, like the daughters, right? That's what
אביי Abaye said. רב אשי Rav Ashi says no, למטה lemata כלמעלה
means this is called למטה lemata
and this is called למעלה. lemala. Why? That's bizarre, right? But he
says because למטה means less severe of a relationship, and למעלה lemala
means a more severe of a relationship. So since these are further
removed, they are a weaker relationship, and since these are closer, they're
a heavier relationship. So it's still the same point, how do you
know to forbid the grandmother-in-law like the mother-in-law? and it's still going
to be the same point that we learn it out from the
case of the daughters. It's just a question what the terms are
referring to. Okay, so the bottom line is however you exactly parse
the למעלה כלמטה it's saying, we get שריפה srefah here because of
the mother-in-law and then we apply it to his to his daughters,
and we get two generations by the זמה זמה zimah zimah by
applying it up from the daughters to the to the to the
mothers and the grandmothers-in-law. Okay, phew, now we've done all that. Now
here's the question.
The one thing we haven't done is it turned out how do
you know his own daughter, but we'll worry about that later. Okay,
אי מה
היא אין אמה אסורה אף הוא אין אמו אסורה. Ei mah hi
ein imah asurah af hu ein imo asurah. Ah, as long as
we're making a whole parallel here, so why don't we say the
same way here, right these it goes down, we should make a
connection, maybe the הנה הנה hena hena or whatever connection we're making,
and say not only is he forbidden with his
with his mother, which is explicit in the פסוקים, psukim, but maybe
he should be forbidden with his grandmother. And ironically here,
through a קל וחומר Kal Vachomer he's not. A man's grandmother is
only forbidden to him, his biological grandmother is only forbidden to him
rabbinically. Whereas his wife's grandmother is forbidden to him biblically. Okay so
it's saying but look, by parallel, so far everything has been parallel,
right? So by parallel, maybe maybe his own grandmother should be forbidden
to him. How do we say why should we say not that
way? Okay, so let's take a look. אי מה היא אין אמה
אסורה אף הוא אין אמו אסורה, Ei mah hi ein imah asurah
af hu ein imo asurah, and we know that's not true. So
אמר אביי אמר קרא, amar Abaye amar kra, the verse says אמך
היא, imecha hi, לא תגלה ערותה. lo tegaleh ervatah. משום אמו אתה
מחייבו ואי אתה מחייבו משום אם אמו. Mishum imo atah mechayvo ve’ei
atah mechayvo mishum em imo. They emphasize she is your mother means
we stop at mother, we don't go any further. רבא אמר, Rava
amar, now רבא Rava says look, forget that. Even without that פסוק,
pasuk, I could explain to you why it's impossible based on the
linking of the two to say there should be true by grandmother.
בין למאן דאמר דון מינה ומינה ובין למאן דאמר דון מינה ואוקי
באתרה. Bein leman deamar don minah uminah uvein leman deamar don minah
ve’okei be’atrah. And this is a very fascinating two like different methodologies.
If I link if I link two things A to B and
to learn out a particular הלכה. halachah. When I so if I
learn like A and B are linked so if something is true
by B it's also going to be true by A. Once I
take that הלכה... halachah... halacha that's true by B and I apply
it to A. Do I then say I just applied that one
little הלכה halacha by B, but once I put it in the
A category, its parameters are defined by the normal way in which
A category works? Or do I say no, if I'm going to
be borrowing a הלכה halacha from B, I have to take it
in the whole context in which it appears in B and apply
it in A. So that's דון מינה ומינה, don mina umina, learn
from it and from it. If you're taking something from B and
applying it to A, you gotta take it with its entire context
from B. Or דון מינה, don mina, learn from it, but ואוקי
באתרה, veoki beatra, then put it in the new location and have
it defined by the new context. Okay, you hear the two? So
let's see how this applies. He says, whichever way you would normally
do it, לא אתיא, lo asya, you cannot learn out
from here to here to say to be grandmother.
Let's see. למאן דאמר leman deamar דון מינה ומינה, don mina umina,
learn from it with its original context. So מה היא אם אמה
אסורה, mah hi eim ima asura, אף הוא נמי אם אמה אסורה.
af hu nami eim ima asura. The thing would be the same
way when it comes to his wife, grandmother is forbidden, when it
comes to him, grandmother is forbidden. That's what we would want to
learn out. The thing we're learning out is grandmother is forbidden. Okay,
but the larger context is what is the punishment. Okay, ומינה, umina,
so that's דון מינה ומינה. don mina umina. Now let's take the
context in which it occurs. ומה היא בשרפה אף הוא נמי בשרפה.
umah hi bisreifa af hu nami bisreifa. The same way right, her
grandmother is שרפה, sreifa, if we were to forbid his grandmother by
analogy, if it's דון מינה ומינה, don mina umina, he'd get שרפה.
sreifa. Everybody with me? But his own mother the Torah tells you
is סקילה. skila. So now we've got a little logical problem.
Okay, ומה היא בשרפה umah hi bisreifa אף הוא נמי בשרפה. af
hu nami bisreifa. למאן דאמר leman deamar שרפה חמורה sreifa chamura איכא
למיפרך. ika lemefrach. But one minute, if שרפה sreifa is weightier, that
should prevent you from making the learning altogether. נהי שכן אמו בשרפה,
nahish k'in imo bisreifa, תאמר בהו שאמו בסקילה? tamer behu she'imo biskila?
How can you say oh, she her grandmother is forbidden and him
his grandmother should be forbidden. No, we know that she her mother
whatever is weightier because her mother is שרפה, sreifa, his mother is
סקילה. skila. So therefore since this whole category is weightier, we shouldn't
be able to learn it out. Number one. ועוד, ve'od, אמו בסקילה
אם אמו בשרפה? imo biskila eim imo bisreifa? The conclusion would be
crazy. Not only is this weightier and we can't learn out from
her mother to his mother, but how could it be that his
own mother is סקילה skila and his grandmother is שרפה? sreifa? How
could it be a weightier punishment? ועוד, ve'od, מה היא לא חלקת
בה בין אמא לאם אמא, mah hi lo chalakta bah bein ima
le'eim ima, אף הוא נמי לא תחלוק בין אמא לאם אמא. af
hu nami lo tachalok bein ima le'eim ima. And forgetting which is
weightier, by her mother and grandmother get the same punishment. By him
they're getting different punishments. So there's no if you're going to apply
the same principle, מינה ומינה, mina umina, if you're going to learn
out grandmother it's going to come with שרפה, sreifa, okay, so then
it's crazy. Then there's no logic that grandmother should be שרפה sreifa
and mother should be
סקילה. skila. Okay, ולמאן דאמר סקילה חמורה, U-le-man De-amar Skeela Chamura, even
if stoning is weightier, מהאי קשיא לא נידנא. mehai kushya lo nidana.
So some of the earlier things that oh how could it be
that this is worse than the grandmother's fine. Forget the question of
worse. Forget that it's worse. Whichever one is worse, if there's no
here mother and grandmother are the same and according to this mother
and grandmother would be different. And that would be enough to tell
you that you cannot learn it out because it doesn't maintain the
consistency. So if you say דון מינה ומינה don mina umina you
can't learn it out because that would get שרפה sreifa and this
would be סקילה skila and that wouldn't make any sense. Now how
about if you say דון מינה
ואוקי באתרה. don mina veoki beatra. ולמאן דאמר uleman deamar according to
the one that says דון מינה ואוקי באתרה, don mina veoki beatra,
we'll learn out the principle that she gets that it's forbidden and
she gets put to death. But then we're going to put it
in the context of mother and in the context of mother it's
סקילה skila not שרפה. sreifa. מה היא אם אמה אסורה, mah hi
eim ima asura, the same way by the by the wife grandmother
is forbidden, אף הוא נמי אם אמה אסורה, af hu nami eim
ima asura, his grandmother is forbidden. But that's מינה. mina. ואוקי באתרה,
veoki beatra, but then put it in that context. מה התם הוא
בשרפה, mah hatam hu bisreifa, by the grandmother it's שרפה, sreifa, by
the wife's grandmother it's שרפה, sreifa, אבל הכא בסקילה. aval hacha biskila.
You understand the דון מינה ואוקי באתרה? don mina veoki beatra? Yes,
we learned out forbidden but in the context of סקילה. skila. כאשכחן
באמו, keashkachan be'imo, like the mother, that's the current context. So now
here's why that can't work. למאן דאמר leman deamar שרפה חמורה sreifa
chamura איכא למיפרך. ika lemefrach. Fine. So fine, they're both going to
get סקילה. skila. But you still could say, how can I make
an analogy? If her grandmother is forbidden his grandmother should be forbidden.
She grandmother is forbidden because it's getting a weightier punishment, she clearly
this is more problematic because it's שרפה, sreifa, this is only סקילה.
skila. So just because here you go up to grandmother doesn't mean
here you go up to grandmother. Okay, איכא למיפרך. ika lemefrach.
מה להיא שכן אמו בשרפה, mah lehi sheken imo bisreifa, תאמר בהו
שאמו בסקילה? tamer behu she'imo biskila? Okay, so you can't so even
if this would be consistent סקילה, skila, you could say this is
a weightier category, it gets
שרפה. sreifa. הוא כהיא. Hoo ke-Hee. מה היא לא חלקת בין בתה
לאם אמה, Mah Hee Lo Chalkta Bayn Beeta Le-Aim Eema, אף הוא
לא תחלוק בין בתה לאם אמו. Af Hoo Lo Tachlok Bayn Beeta
Le-Aim Imo. Look, there's another consistency problem. See, her granddaughter gets שריפה
Sreifa and her grandmother gets שריפה, Sreifa, right? If this is getting
סקילה, Skeela, we've got a problem. His granddaughter gets שריפה, Sreifa, but
his grandmother gets סקילה. Skeela. So it's not going to remain consistent.
Okay? So אף הוא לא תחלוק בין בתה לאם אמו. Af Hoo
Lo Tachlok Bayn Beeta Le-Aim Imo. Okay, fine. So ולמאן דאמר uleman
deamar סקילה חמורה, skila chamura,
even if סקילה Skeela is a weightier punishment, מהאי קושיא לא נידנה,
Me-hai Kushia Lo Nidna, that question prevents you from learning it out
because it doesn't really matter what's weightier or less weightier. The problem
is that it's not consistent. That if this is going to get
סקילה Skeela then it's based on an analogy to his wife, the
analogy will fail because by the wife daughter and granddaughter are the
same and by him grandmother and daughter or granddaughter are not the
same. So there's no way by analogy to learn it out because
the analogy just fails. Okay, so since it's going to fail on
one part we cannot learn it out and you're left with the
irony that besides that the mother's סקילה Skeela and these are שריפה
Sreifa and שריפה Sreifa is weightier than סקילה, Skeela, okay, you do
not go up another generation by the mother. So we basically have
proven all of this and we've proven why you don't go up
and the one thing we sort of have yet to directly address
is how do you know his own daughter as and not just
his granddaughter which is sort of a קל וחומר Kal Vachomer but
we will get to that. Okay, we will address this.